# Luiz Gonzaga dos Santos Filho, MBA

Vancouver, Canada

mww.luiz.dev

🔽 lfilho@gmail.com

in /luizgonzaga

/luizgonzaga

/lfilho

/lfilho

A people first geek building impactful products and high-performing, engaged teams for ~21.5 years.

I grow organizations of all sizes with efficient and low touch processes.

I grow people with empathy, trust, mentorship and accountability.

I'm continually upskilling myself and love sharing what I know. Feel free to check some of my testimonials and recommendations on my LinkedIn and Topmate profiles.

For a more verbose version of my resumé, visit luiz.dev/cv/verbose.

## **Experience**

## 🗓 Software Engineering Manager → Senior Software Engineering Manager @ Coursera

Seb 2021 – present

- · Cultivated talent: managed several teams and charters, promoted engineers to Senior, Staff and Manager
- Drove Enterprise growth: led key Enterprise initiatives and products, unlocking several millions of dollars in revenue yearly
- Enhanced organizational efficiency: conceptualized, implemented and improved several team and org-wide processes, resulting in improved metrics and accountability, reduced touchpoints and better-informed leadership decision-making
- Championed DE&I and well-being: authored and drove different org-wide policies around DE&I, measurably increased our hiring pipeline's
  diversity and maintained highest team retention in the org



## Software Engineering Manager II → Software Engineering Manager III @ Amazon / AWS

**(**) Sep 2017 – Dec 2020

- At Amazon Payments: led a multi-year payments integrations effort involving international and cross-department collaboration to launch Amazon in Turkey; drove early adoption of PSD2 regulations, ensuring European market compliance ahead of competitors; owned Payment on Delivery for the Indian market
- At AWS Route53: hired and grew a team from scratch; measurabely improved operational efficiency, accessibility, and usability across five
  different products; owned multiple product roadmaps and delivered two global product launches, expanding AWS Route53's presence into
  new markets and regions
- Drove organizational change and fostered inclusion: improved our sourcing efficiency by ~32% and our pipeline's diversity by ~11%;
   championed an engineering-wide policy to promote inclusion and belonging; as a certified Cultural Competences for Teams instructor,
   trained hundreds of leaders and engineers around diversity and inclusion
- Mentored and supported other managers: served on the Software Engineering Manager Peer Advisory board, providing guidance and support to peers



#### Senior Frontend Engineer → Frontend Team Lead @ Brandwatch

**(**S) Apr 2016 – Feb 2017

- As the Frontend team lead: helped the PM with agile ceremonies and backlog prioritization; liason with the team manager in the UK headquarters
- As a Senior Frontend Engineer: worked existing and new feature development on Brandwatch's main product (Analytics); refactored thousands of files o0 a 5-year-old jQuery codebase, improving bundle size, patching security vulnerabilities, and enabling new features to be used



#### Full-stack engineer @ X-Team

O Apr 2015 – Apr 2015

• Short collaboration with X-Team's CTO researching, planning and developing the next phase of X-Labs (their open source initiative) and other internal projects involving IndexedDB



## Software Engineering Manager @ DataEasy

( Jun 2014 – Mar 2016

- Led Engineering Transformation: directed a company-wide shift to modern DevOps and ChatOps practices, including Git, SemVer, CI
  pipelines, live application monitoring, automated release management, enabling higher quality and faster releases and allowing the IT
  department to stay leaner
- · Championed Process Improvement: mapped all engineering processes, reduced touchpoints and staffing needs
- Fostered growth and upskilling: partnered with a local university to provide automated testing courses for senior engineers, streamlining testing cycles and reducing release bottlenecks

#(Scrum)(XP)(Kanban)(SemVer)(BPM)(Software	Testing Freetest Testlink DevOps Jenkins Continuous	Integration Shell Scripting Java EE Maven GitHub New Relic Node Docker Management
Senior Frontend Engineer @ Brandwate	ch	() Apr 2013 – Nov 2013
<ul> <li>Developed their main product line: bra</li> <li>Wrote codemods to refactor thousands merge</li> </ul>		educing code review length and improving time to
# (Node) (Javascript) (Require) (Backbone)	Underscore HTML 5 CSS 3 Highcharts JQuery Musta	ache BDD Jasmine Phantom REST Scrum GitHub JIRA
Senior Frontend Engineer → Frontend T	eam Lead @ Content Fleet	() Apr 2012 – Mar 2013
optimization initiatives, significantly rec	EST APIs and core MVC applications. Led mobil ducing network calls and minimizing source code frontend strategy, conventions, quality, performations.	·
# Node MongoDB Javascript	Require Backbone Underscore HTML 5 CSS 3 Highch	narts)(jQuery)(REST)(Scrum)(SVN)(Shell Script)(Pivotal Tracker)
Full-stack Engineer @ Goiás State Gove	ernment	Sev 2007 – Mar 2012
over 200k people		CM) system, supporting payroll and other features for
<ul> <li>Led several performance, usability and</li> </ul>	d accessibility improvements  # (Java EE)	Velocity)(SQL)(HTML)(Javascript)(jQuery)(CSS 3)(SVN)(UX)
	.,	
Junior Full-stack Engineer @ DR Sistem		© 2004 – 2005
<ul> <li>At Interagi, I developed CROD application</li> <li>At DR Sistemas, I developed a Backer</li> </ul>	tions and did some programatic image processind application for the public law sector	ng
	# Java EE Struts Hib	remate SQL JSP PHP MySQL HTML CSS SVN CVS
Misc Software Engineering & Consultan	ncy gigs @ Freelancer	Jan 2003 – Dec 2014
<ul> <li>SENAC Goiás, Goiânia, Brazil — Cons of dynamic versus compiled languages</li> </ul>		roductivity tools, agile methodologies and comparison
# 12 Factor Apps Web Development Team	Coaching Individual Coaching Agile Methodologies Web Lar	nguages Web Services REST Software Testing Software Quality Continuous Integration
Other		
Over 23 experiences as an instructor or speak of them at luiz.dev/cv/verbose.	ker and 7 volunteer positions around leadership,	web development, community and the arts. See all
Education		
Business Process Management, MBA  IT Management Institute (IGTI) – Brazil	Computer Engineering, Bachelor Federal University of Goiás – Brazil Extra studies on Software Engineering Relative average grade: 85%	Computer Science, Visiting Student  Saint Mary's University – Canada  i Emerging Leaders of America Scholarship  2nd round on Trumped Competition
Languages		
	▲☑ English — Fluent	▲☑ German & Spanish — Basic
Portuguese — Native	Liigiisii — Fidelit	